I've noticed that almost all the really
good machine learning practitioners tend
to have a very sophisticated
understanding of bias and variance.
Bias and variance is one of those
concepts that's easy to learn but
difficult to master.
Even if you think you've seen
the basic concepts of bias and
variance is often more nuanced
to it than you'd expect.
In the deep learning era, another trend
is that there's been less discussion of
what's called the bias variance trade off.
You might have heard this thing called
the bias variance trade off, but
in the deep learning era,
there's less of a trade off.
So we still talk about bias,
we still talk about variance, but
we just talk less about
the bias variance trade off.
Let's see what this means.
Let's say you have a data
set that looks like this.
If you fit a straight line to the data,
maybe you get a logistic
regression fit to that.
This is not a very good fit to the data,
and so there's a cause of high bias.
Or we say that this is
underfitting the data.
On the opposite end, if you fit
an incredibly complex classifier,
maybe a deep neural network.
Or a new network with
a lot of hidden units,
maybe you can fit the data perfectly.
But that doesn't look
like a great fit either.
So this is a classifier
with high variance,
and this is overfitting the data.
And there might be some classifier
in between with a medium level of
complexity that maybe
fits a curve like that.
That looks like a much more
reasonable fit to the data.
So that's the, and call that just
right somewhere in each tree.
So in a 2d example like this,
with just two features, x1 and x2,
you can plot the data and
visualize bias and variance.
In high dimensional problems,
you can't plot the data and
visualize the decision boundary.
Instead, there are couple different
metrics that we'll look at to try to
understand bias and variance.
So, continuing our example of
cat picture classification,
where that's a positive example and
that's a negative example.
The two key numbers to look
at to understand bias and
variance will be the trading set error and
the dev set, or the development set error.
So, for the sake of argument,
let's say that recognizing
cats in pictures is something that
people can do nearly perfectly, right?
And so let's say your trading size
error is 1% and your dev set error is,
for the sake of argument,
let's say, is 11%.
So in this example, you're doing
very well on the training set, but
you're doing relatively poorly
on the development set.
So this looks like you might
have overfit the training set.
That somehow you're not generalizing well
to this holdout cost validation set to
development set.
And so if you have an example like this,
we will say this has high variance.
So by looking at the training set
error and the development set error,
you would be able to render a diagnosis
of your algorithm having high variance.
Now let's say that you measure your
training set in your dev set error and
you get a different result.
Let's say that your
training set error is 15%.
I'm writing your training set error in
the top row and your dev set error is 16%.
In this case, assuming that
humans achieve roughly 0% error,
that humans can look at these pictures and
just tell if it's cat or not.
Then it looks like the algorithm is not
even doing very well on the training set.
So if it's not even fitting
the training data, as seen that well,
then this is underfitting the data.
And so this algorithm has high bias.
But in contrast,
this is actually generalizing at
a reasonable level to the dev set, whereas
performance of the dev set is only 1%
worse as performance on the training set.
So this algorithm has a problem of high
bias because it's not even training,
it's not even fitting
the training set well.
This is similar to the leftmost
plot we had on the previous slide.
Now here's another example.
Let's say that you have
15% trading set error.
So that's pretty high bias.
But when you evaluate on a dev set,
it does even worse., maybe it does 30%.
In this case, I would diagnose
this algorithm as having high bias
because it's not doing that well on
the trading set and high variance.
So this is really
the worst of both worlds.
And one last example, if you have 0.5
training set error and 1% dev set error.
Then maybe our users are quite happy that
you have a cad costly with only 1% error,
then this would have low bias and
low variance.
One subtlety that I'll
just briefly mention, but
we'll leave to a later
video to discuss in detail.
Is that this analysis is predicated
on the assumption that human
level performance gets nearly 0% error.
Or more generally they're the optimal
error, sometimes called Bayes error for
the so
the bayesian optimal error is nearly 0%.
I don't want to go into detail on
this in this particular video.
But it turns out that if the optimal error
or the Bayes error were much higher,
say it were 15%.
Then if you look at this classifier,
15% is actually perfectly reasonable for
training set.
And you wouldn't say it as high bias and
also have pretty low variance.
So the case of how to analyze bias and
variance when no classifier
can do very well.
For example,
if you have really blurry images so
that even a human or just no system
could possibly do very well.
Then maybe Bayes error is much higher.
And then there's some details of
how this analysis will change.
But leaving aside this subtlety for now,
the takeaway is that by looking
at your trading set error.
You can get a sense of how well you're
fitting at least the training data.
And so
that tells you if you have a bias problem.
And then looking at how much higher your
error goes when you go from the training
set to the dev set.
That should give you a sense of
how bad is the variance problem.
So are you doing a good job generalizing
from the training set to the dev set that
gives you a sense of your variance?
All this is under the assumption that
the Bayes error is quite small and
that your train and your death sets
are drawn from the same distribution.
If those assumptions are violated, there's
more sophisticated analysis you could do,
which we'll talk about in the later video.
Now, on the previous slide you saw what
high bias, high variance looks like, and
I guess you have the sense of what
a good classifier looks like.
What does high bias and
high variance looks like?
It's kind of the worst of both worlds.
So you remember we said that
a classifier like this,
a linear classifier, has high bias
because it under fits the data.
So this would be a classifier
that is mostly linear and
therefore under fits the data.
We'll join this in purple.
But if somehow your classifier
does some weird things,
then it's actually overfitting
parts of the data as well.
So the classifier that I drew in purple
has both high bias and high variance.
There's high bias because by
being a mostly linear classifier,
it's just not fitting this
quadratic light shape that well.
But by having too much flexibility in
the middle, it somehow gets this example.
And this example overfits
those two examples as well.
So this classifier kind of has high
bias because it was mostly linear, but
you needed maybe a curve function,
a quadratic function.
And it has high variance because it had
too much flexibility to fit those two
mislabeled outlier examples
in the middle as well.
In case this seems contrived, well, it is.
This example is a little bit
contrived in two dimensions, but
with very high dimensional inputs.
You actually do get things with
high bias in some regions and
high variance in some regions.
And so it is possible to get cross files
like this in high dimensional inputs
that seem less contrived.
So, to summarize, you've seen how by
looking at your algorithm's error
on the training set and
your algorithm's error on the dev set.
You can try to diagnose whether it has
problem of high bias or high variance, or
maybe both, or maybe neither.
And depending on whether your algorithm
suffers from bias or variance,
it turns out that there
are different things you could try.
So in the next video, I want to present
to you what I call a basic recipe for
machine learning.
That lets you more systematically try
to improve your algorithm depending on
whether as high bias or
high variance issues.
So let's go on to the next video.